<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Brexit on Arguable Intelligence</title>
    <link>https://ojmason.github.io/categories/brexit/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Brexit on Arguable Intelligence</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <copyright>(C) Oliver Mason</copyright>
    <atom:link href="https://ojmason.github.io/categories/brexit/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Constitutional Failure</title>
      <link>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/constitutional-failure/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Aug 2017 16:02:02 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/constitutional-failure/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Leaving aside that Brexit is a political disaster in itself, the way the UK got into it
shows a deeper failure of the political system: a lack of resilience to catastrophic events.
The term &amp;ldquo;catastrophic&amp;rdquo; is here meant in the sense of &amp;ldquo;some event that causes enormous change
(usually bad)&amp;ldquo;, though in my view Brexit is a catastrophe in the other, main sense as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A constitutional system should protect the state from radical change. The Weimar Republic failed,
as its constitution was not able to prevent the rise of fascism and its own abolition by an elected
government. The current German constitution requires a much bigger majority for any changes to the constitution
itself as a consequence: no more simple majorities that can empower a dictatorship as happened in 1933.
And the current chancellor cannot be voted out unless another candidate has a majority, another lesson
learned from 1933, where the democratic centre got squeezed from the extreme left and right wings, robbing
it of a majority without providing a positive alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The American system is currently being tested on the powers of the president. It was fine for the president
to make decisions by decree against the majority in the elected chambers as long as it was the good guy Obama;
but now Trump is in power, he can use the same powers to do things we don&amp;rsquo;t like. As Dan Carlin says in his
&lt;em&gt;Common Sense&lt;/em&gt; podcast, you want to be careful with who gets the power in case the people in charge change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British system failed, as a purely advisory referendum which arguably had no real majority in the population
and was called for no particular reason apart from appeasing a backbench group in a political party suddenly
became taken for granted, with enormous consequences for the economy and the political system of the country.
Regardless how it pans out, it will have caused great damage to the economy and the political status of the UK,
and will have wasted huge amounts of civil servants&amp;rsquo; time in trying to deal with re-writing four decades of laws
and regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the UK had a functioning constitution, a decision of this enormity could not happen with a majority of just 1.5%.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>