<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Misc on Arguable Intelligence</title>
    <link>https://ojmason.github.io/categories/misc/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Misc on Arguable Intelligence</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <copyright>(C) Oliver Mason</copyright>
    <atom:link href="https://ojmason.github.io/categories/misc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title> First Post</title>
      <link>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2017 14:40:17 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/first-post/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;first-post&#34;&gt;First Post&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m trying blogging again &amp;ndash; twitter is a bit too sparse for longer rants. And this seems
to be a time for rants. Lots happening in politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, here we go again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update:&lt;/em&gt; I&amp;rsquo;m also going through my previous WordPress log to gather some articles that
might still be interesting, so there will be older articles going back almost a decade
appearing here.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Numerical Illiteracy</title>
      <link>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/numerical-illiteracy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/numerical-illiteracy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note:&lt;/em&gt; This is an older article from the blog I ran while being an academic. Most of the posts
on there are about teaching and learning, but this one is of more general relevance, see also
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ojmason.github.io/longest-chip-in-the-world/&#34;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;hr&gt;
I had a look at our free local newspaper, the &lt;em&gt;Birmingham Mail Extra&lt;/em&gt;.
In this issue is an article titled &amp;ldquo;Suburb is now crime hotspot&amp;rdquo;.
This article has several problems, which are indicative of the
problems of representing what happens &amp;lsquo;out there&amp;rsquo; in the form of a
newspaper article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quinton had very little burglaries, &amp;ldquo;averaging just one or two
burglaries a month&amp;rdquo; over the last nine years. But now, crime has
&amp;ldquo;shot up by 29%&amp;rdquo;, more than the rest of Birmingham where crime only
rose by 21%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find this rather misleading, and I worked through an example with
the kids at the dinner table, which illustrates the problem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suburb A had 10 burglaries in 2009, and 12 in 2010. That is an increase of 20%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suburb B had 4 burglaries in 2009, and 5 in 2010. Increase of 25%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suburb C had 1 burglary in 2009, and 2 in 2010. A whopping 100% increase.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;First lesson:&lt;/em&gt; percentage increase is meaningless unless everybody
started in the same place. Why do developing economies have higher
growth rates than Europe and the US? Because the percentage looks
bigger. If you double your output from 100 cars to 200 cars you
increase by 100%, but to maintain that rate you will have to produce
an additional 200 cars the year after, and then 400, 800 etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Second lesson:&lt;/em&gt; without a fixed reference point (such as burglaries
per 1000 inhabitants) you have no idea whether the risk of your
house being burgled is high or low. Everything is relative, but you
still need a fixed point to evaluate things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Third lesson:&lt;/em&gt; this is not mentioned, but is that difference between
29% and 21% statistically significant? With &amp;ldquo;one or two burglaries
a month&amp;rdquo;, the variation seems rather high, given those small numbers.
So if there was one extra or one fewer burglaries, how would the
29% change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Final lesson:&lt;/em&gt; be careful with calling places &amp;ldquo;crime hotspot&amp;rdquo; when
your statistics are that shaky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I don&amp;rsquo;t expect a staff reporter at the &lt;em&gt;Birmingham Mail&lt;/em&gt; to apply
the same rigour as a scientist (or any other, non-science researcher),
but the way the article is presented is simply misleading. To me
this sounds like a scare story being created out of some random
statistics. I don&amp;rsquo;t know whether that is the case, and maybe Quinton
is really a crime-ridden area, but I cannot tell from the few facts
given to me in the article. The reason for this development given
in the paper is that there are now 5 fewer policemen covering
Quinton. Is there really such a cast-iron correlation between
policemen and crime rate? How about the influence of the recession
on crime? And how many policemen were there before the cut? 50? 500?
5000?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now have more questions and know less than I did before reading
that article!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The longest Chip in the World</title>
      <link>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/the-longest-chip-in-the-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Dec 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/the-longest-chip-in-the-world/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In his &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0465045669?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=phrasysnlp-21&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=19450&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0465045669&#34;&gt;Metamagical Themas: Questing for the Essence of Mind and
Pattern&lt;/a&gt;,
Douglas Hofstadter talks about &lt;em&gt;numerical literacy&lt;/em&gt;, the
ability to understand large numbers. This is especially important
when state budgets are thrown around which deal with billions of
pounds or euros. At some point you just lose all feeling for
quantities, as they are all so unimaginably large and abstract. He
then goes on to pose some rough calculation questions, such as “How
many cigarettes are smoked in the US every day?” – you start with
some estimates, and then work out an answer, which might be near
the order of magnitude of the right answer (which we of course don’t
know). Quite an interesting and useful mental exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday we had Fish &amp;amp; Chips for dinner. The girls were comparing
the sizes of their chips, and then we came on to the topic of the
longest chip in the world. Obviously, with ‘proper’ chips this is
limited by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.france-today.com/2009/12/longest-chip-in-world-isof-course.html&#34;&gt;size of the source potato&lt;/a&gt;.
However, assuming that industrially
produced chips are made of mashed potato formed into chip-shapes,
there is not really any fixed limit on the length. So, thinking
of Hofstadter, I asked them how many potatoes we would need to make
a chip that spans around the whole world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rough assumptions: one potato contains enough matter to produce
10cm worth of chip (the thickness is not specified). So, how many
potatoes do we need for one metre of chip? This is also useful to
practice basic primary-school-level maths… – 10. How many for a
kilometre? 10,000. How many kilometres do we need to span the world?
Roughly 40,000 km. So how many potatoes do we need? 400 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next question is whether there are enough potatoes in the world
to do this. Assuming a potato weighs 100g, how much do our 400
million potatoes weigh? 40 million kilogrammes, or 40,000 (metric)
tons. What is the world’s potato production? According to &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Potato&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;,
this is 315 million metric tons, so plenty enough. Now, if we were
to turn the annual potato crop into one long chip, how many times
would it go round the Earth? 7,875 times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, with a bit of basic maths (and Wikipedia for the data) you can
make maths exciting for kids, practice how to multiply and divide,
teach problem-solving, and have fun at the same time. And they also
get a feeling for numbers: 400 million – that’s how many potatoes
you need for a chip to span the Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meteorites</title>
      <link>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/meteorites/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/meteorites/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While clearing out a decade’s worth of paper from my office I came
across an article in the Feb 2003 issue of the university’s in-house
paper, &lt;em&gt;Buzz&lt;/em&gt;. In one article, the following extract struck me: &lt;em&gt;…artists
had acquired a meteorite from a meteorite dealer in Scotland.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several questions come to mind: Can you make a living as a meteorite
dealer? I guess there are more meteorites hitting Earth as one would
think, not all of course big enough to make (no pun intended) an
impact. And why Scotland? Is Scotland especially prone to being hit
by meteorites?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://curious.astro.cornell.edu/about-us/75-our-solar-system/comets-meteors-and-asteroids/meteorites/313-how-many-meteorites-hit-earth-each-year-intermediate&#34;&gt;Thanks to the web&lt;/a&gt;,
the first question can be supplemented by a
useful snippet of information: &lt;em&gt;Over the whole surface area of Earth,
that translates to 18,000 to 84,000 meteorites bigger than 10 grams
per year.&lt;/em&gt; But of course 70% of that end up in the sea, and most of
them never make it through the atmosphere in the first place. I
also don’t want to speculate how much demand there is for meteorites,
other than from conceptual artists and perhaps astrophysicists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update:&lt;/em&gt;
I didn&amp;rsquo;t realise at the time that a few years later I would be clearing out
my office for good, due to a change of jobs. It took me more than a whole week.
In retrospect I should&amp;rsquo;ve just dumped everything into a big skip, as the papers
I carefully sorted into different piles have not been touched since, and are
probably unlikely to be touched ever again, before being thrown into the bin
a final time!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>