<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Arguable Intelligence</title>
    <link>https://ojmason.github.io/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Arguable Intelligence</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <copyright>(C) Oliver Mason</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2017 22:15:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://ojmason.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>National Novel Generation Month -- Day 6</title>
      <link>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/national-novel-generation-month----day-6/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2017 22:15:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/national-novel-generation-month----day-6/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Day 6 &amp;ndash; but today is November 24th&amp;hellip; this just serves to show how hard it is to combine a side project
with a full-time job, a family, and other hobbies! The last two weekends I spent sailing at two all-weekend
races (Northampton and Draycote), and in the evenings I am generally too busy with other things. And I don&amp;rsquo;t
want to &amp;lsquo;pull an all-nighter&amp;rsquo;, as it&amp;rsquo;s not a sustainable way to do things. However, today I got a few things
done:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The central element of my project is a &amp;lsquo;world simulator&amp;rsquo;, in which the characters act out their desires, follow
their goals, and interact in (hopefully) interesting ways, which I will then harvest to generate a story from.
The core of the simulator is a planner: you feed in the characters&amp;rsquo; goals, and they will then find a way of
doing what they need to do in order to achieve them. The planning algorithm I&amp;rsquo;m using is called Goal Oriented
Action Planning (GOAP), basically a back-ward chaining algorithm: Starting from the goal, you work backwards
to see which actions get you to your goal. Each action has a post-condition (which would be matched to the
goal), and a pre-condition (which becomes the new goal). You select an action whose post-condition matches
some of the character&amp;rsquo;s goal conditions, and then see how you get there. Each action also has a cost associated
with it, which allows you to choose a more efficient path in case there are several options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have today managed to implement a very basic version of that in Scheme. I&amp;rsquo;m using atomic conditions, but
eventually will have more complicated expressions, but it is a first step. For several toy scenarioes the
planner does indeed find suitable solutions, which are paths through a network of states. Adjusting this to
the final world representation should not be too much of an issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have resigned myself to not finishing this system by the end of the month. But I&amp;rsquo;ve made a start, and will try
to get this continued throughout the year, so that I have a novel ready by NaNoGenMo 2018&amp;hellip; On the positive side,
my Scheme programming is getting better, and I have loads of ideas about what to implement over the coming year.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>National Novel Generation Month -- Day 5</title>
      <link>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/national-novel-generation-month----day-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2017 11:05:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/national-novel-generation-month----day-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today just some minor implementations; a start on basic functions to maintain the world: add and update character
information, etc. All rather mundane yet necessary stuff. More reading in &lt;em&gt;Inside Computer Understanding&lt;/em&gt; by
Schank and Riesbeck, and the realisation that I really have to cut down things if I want to get anything done by
the end of the month. The more interesting part for me is the natural language generation, so I might have to give up
on generating an interesting world in favour of more trivial events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think back with sentimental feelings to the days of being a student &amp;ndash; no job, no family, but lots of spare time
to work on interesting stuff like this. I think that is the real benefit of a university education: the freedom to
research pet projects!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to make it worthwhile, I will develop the world simulator in a modular way, so that more complexity
can always be added in later on. New plans or goals, new actions, or whatever else is required to make it more
realistic. I might end up with a version of the Sims&amp;hellip; but with a narrative text interface, rather than a graphical
one. Let&amp;rsquo;s see how far I get.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>National Novel Generation Month -- Day 4</title>
      <link>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/national-novel-generation-month----day-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2017 23:25:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/national-novel-generation-month----day-4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today is only day 4, as I was too busy to do anything on the project yesterday. I spent a bit
more time on emotions, exploring the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Contrasting_and_categorization_of_emotions#Plutchik.27s_wheel_of_emotions&#34;&gt;Wheel of Emotions&lt;/a&gt;
in a bit more detail. Implementation-wise I made a start on the module that generates and handles characters.
From the wheel of emotions it is possible to derive a number of secondary emotions, and as I use
emotion &amp;lsquo;coordinates&amp;rsquo; to evaluate the stance of a character towards other characters, this should
allow for a decent modelling of interpersonal relations. I&amp;rsquo;m still not sure how this will influence
decision making. There will probably have to be some evaluation function which assigns a numerical
score to each option, and that will be modified by the stance of the character towards any affected
characters, and also the character&amp;rsquo;s own current emotional state. If they are furious, they might
actually choose an irrational option that harms themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When rendering this as a story, it might be worth looking at state changes, and possibly to add changes
to emotional states as annotations to any activities that are going on, so that we can generate text like
&lt;em&gt;A did some action, and it filled B with anger.&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;A was overjoyed to see B again.&lt;/em&gt; &amp;ndash; obviously, it
is always better to describe emotional states indirectly where possible, but that seems to hard for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given how little time I can devote to the project, I think I will have to scale it down a bit if I want to
have anything ready by the end of the month. I might always try to continue working on it afterwards for
the more ambitious &amp;lsquo;stretch goals&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the to-do list now is the representation of world knowledge, both the objective &amp;lsquo;truth&amp;rsquo; and the characters&amp;rsquo;
individual views of it. Then the world simulator/planner, and then a few basic aims. At that point I should
have a simple TaleSpin working, which I can extend with more details. I would then add more aims and actions to it as I go
along, and start work on the routine to generate the story from the world log, and finally the verbalisation,
which will be a slightly more sophisticated clone of Mumble.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>National Novel Generation Month -- Day 3</title>
      <link>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/national-novel-generation-month----day-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2017 17:41:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/national-novel-generation-month----day-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Now that I have a basic (abstract) plot outline and some idea about the characters&amp;rsquo; emotions,
I need to think about what drives them. &lt;a href=&#34;../national-novel-generation-month----day-2/&#34;&gt;Yesterday&lt;/a&gt; I listed some aims that
the system would understand. So, each character gets a set of initial aims that they are trying to
achieve. Ideally there would be some conflict built in, for example a love interest: two separate
characters want to fall in love with the same person. As they attempt to win that person&amp;rsquo;s heart,
they might clash. Or, decide to live in an open relationship together as a triple, who knows!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That would also make it easy to implement some of &lt;a href=&#34;../national-novel-generation-month----day-1/&#34;&gt;Propp&amp;rsquo;s functions&lt;/a&gt;: the
&lt;em&gt;interdiction&lt;/em&gt; would mean that the hero is told one of his aims is not allowed. And the &lt;em&gt;interdiction-violation&lt;/em&gt;
would mean that the hero ignores that, and keep it as an aim. Alternatively, a friend&amp;rsquo;s aim could be disallowed,
and the hero would try to achieve the aim for the friend, such as acquire an object and give it to the friend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step then is to annotate the narrative functions with actions and aims; for example, &lt;em&gt;absentation&lt;/em&gt;
could be an &lt;em&gt;atrans&lt;/em&gt; of a friend to a location as an action, and the same for the hero as an aim, as the hero
wants to be with their friend. There might be some conflicting aim (such as staying at home, protecting the
family), but the resolution might be that the friend starts feeling sad when away from their home environment,
leading to the aim of coming back home, which then achieves the hero&amp;rsquo;s aim as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also need to start thinking about the &lt;em&gt;World Simulator&lt;/em&gt;, the engine that does all the heavy lifting of
producing the story content. The original idea is to take &lt;em&gt;TaleSpin&lt;/em&gt;, but that might be a bit too simplistic.
After all, it&amp;rsquo;s only really been used for short stories about Joe Bear and Irving Bird. In addition I need
timestamping to keep track of where the various characters are and what they are doing, and a more sophisticated
logging facility, as the simulator log will be fed into the story renderer at the end. I also need to work
with multiple characters at once, so the whole setup needs to be a bit more capable than the original.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>National Novel Generation Month -- Day 2</title>
      <link>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/national-novel-generation-month----day-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2017 23:08:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/national-novel-generation-month----day-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today was more of a research day, apart from some refactoring of yesterday&amp;rsquo;s work. Spent ages trying
to track down an error, which turned out to be one missing level of brackets in a data file. Oh well,
at least I&amp;rsquo;m getting used to debugging Scheme code now (I&amp;rsquo;m using guile to develop this system).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To turn the basic plot into a story, I need to turn the Proppian functions into actions. So I&amp;rsquo;m thinking
of a way of annotating them with what essentially happens in each function. This can be a conceptual
dependency-style structure, but possibly also using some higher level commands than just the basic
primitives that Schank et al used in their work. These would later be expanded into such primitives to
be fed into the language generator at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve also compiled an initial list of &lt;em&gt;aims&lt;/em&gt;, which will drive what the characters will be doing. These
are for example&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;go to location&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;go to person&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;acquire object&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;deliver object&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;acquire information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;defeat person&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;destroy object&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the Propp function &lt;em&gt;departure&lt;/em&gt; maps onto giving the hero the aim &lt;em&gt;go to location&lt;/em&gt;. What that location is,
remains to be seen. It could be the location where a person or object can be found. Whereas &lt;em&gt;reconnaissance&lt;/em&gt;
gives the villain the aim &lt;em&gt;acquire information&lt;/em&gt;. There will be different ways to achieve these aims, which
will involve sub-aims, and hopefully enough variation to generate plenty of different stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking about characters, I&amp;rsquo;ve been looking at emotions. Emotions will determine how characters react, though
I have as yet no clue how that would work. I&amp;rsquo;ve come across a scheme by
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Plutchik&#34;&gt;Robert Plutchik&lt;/a&gt;, which uses eight basic emotions, where two
are paired as counterparts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trust - Disgust&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fear - Anger&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sadness - Joy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Surprise - Anticipation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There would be a scale (-10 to +10 or so), so an emotion item would be a list of four numbers. A character
will have a basic emotional state, but would also have emotion items describing the relationship with other characters.
The states are variable, so if character A is angry, and meets character B, towards whome they feel joy, then they
might become less angry. Obviously a very simplistic way to model something as complicated as human emotions,
but the perfect is the enemy of the good. Especially if you only have one month!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>National Novel Generation Month -- Day 1</title>
      <link>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/national-novel-generation-month----day-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2017 22:29:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/national-novel-generation-month----day-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have this year finally managed to have a go at NaNoGenMo, the attempt to write code to generate a novel, in analogy
to NaNoWriMo, where people try to actually write a novel themselves (which sounds like rather a lot of hard
work). Instead, I will instruct the computer to do it for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My approach will consist of various stages, and at the top level I am planning to generate a broad and abstract
sequence of events that will be fleshed out in subsequent stages. I have chosen the framework of
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vladimir_Propp&#34;&gt;Vladimir Propp&lt;/a&gt;, who analysed Russian folk tales and came up with
a list of 31 &lt;em&gt;narrative functions&lt;/em&gt;, which can be grouped into four distinct sections. I&amp;rsquo;m generating a list of
sections, where each section can have up to four functions, and then I pick the appropriate number of functions
randomly from the list of functions for each section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some constraints, so you cannot have a &lt;em&gt;return&lt;/em&gt; unless you also had a &lt;em&gt;departure&lt;/em&gt; beforehand. I have
implemented a very simple routine which churns out sequences that fulfil their constraints. Quite primitive at
the moment, but perhaps a starting point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some example outputs (for their meaning see the Wikipedia link above) are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;(complicity trickery departure departure villany first-donor-func hero-reaction wedding pursuit)&lt;br /&gt;
This is a bit weird, as there are two departures (but they could be different people), and after
the &lt;em&gt;wedding&lt;/em&gt; there is a &lt;em&gt;pursuit&lt;/em&gt;, so the hero is chased away by a villain after he got married
and rewarded/promoted. Strange, but perhaps leading to an interesting story!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;(interdiction trickery interdiction trickery departure departure departure first-donor-func struggle struggle transfiguration difficult-task)&lt;br /&gt;
Here the hero gets a warning/command twice, and each time a villain attempts some deception. This time,
&lt;em&gt;three&lt;/em&gt; people leave (I think that needs to be cut down to single occurrence only!) and a lot of fighting
is happening.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thing is, I can imagine writing a story around those functions. The
challenge is to see if the computer can do that, too. Still early
days.  The main concern with this whole thing is that the generated
novel will either be trivial and boring, or non-sensical and
incoherent. Probably even both. I am under no illusions that the final result will be worthwhile
reading; but I will only find out at the end!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keeping up Motivation</title>
      <link>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/keeping-up-motivation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2017 20:14:21 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/keeping-up-motivation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last Saturday I took part in our weekly regatta at the sailing club. The first race on a Saturday is an average
lap time one, where all boats start at the same time, and then sail for an hour. There&amp;rsquo;s a yardstick system to
work out which boat sailed the fastest, taking into account the inherent speed differential of the different boats.
I was sailing in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laser_(dinghy)&#34;&gt;Laser&lt;/a&gt;, which is a medium fast boat given the
other ones that were participating in this race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ojmason.github.io/img/laserracing.jpg&#34; caption=&#34;Saturday Afternoon Racing on Edgbaston Reservoir&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a decent start, especially since I&amp;rsquo;m still fairly new to Laser sailing and my boatspeed is not as good as
it could be yet. And my sail is fairly ancient. But it was nice and breezy, and as the field split into two groups,
I managed to stay at the top of the slower group (while the much faster dinghies plus our best club Laser sailor
were disappearing in the distance).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, once I got away from the second group I ended up in &amp;lsquo;no man&amp;rsquo;s land&amp;rsquo;, in a zone between the two fields. Not
really fast enough to catch up with the faster boats, but also far enough away from the rest of the field that I
lost contact. And the inevitable happened: I lost focus, didn&amp;rsquo;t really have anything to gauge my speed, and ended
up being caught by the other boats, unable to keep my position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to that, I rounded one of the marks the wrong way, so technically sailed the wrong course, and had to
retire. As I noticed that during the race, I guess that might also have broken my concentration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not quite sure what to do in this situation. I clearly do better if I have something to compare myself to. Maybe
I should have looked at my watch occasionally to see how long it&amp;rsquo;d take me to do one lap? Of course this doesn&amp;rsquo;t
work perfectly, as the conditions are different all the time with wind shifts and gusts, but it&amp;rsquo;d give me an idea
whether I was faster or slower than previously. Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s just lack of awareness of the boats around me &amp;ndash; when
sailing you need to look at many different things, and it is easy to concentrate too much on the sail settings, but
then lose sight of the overall picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general it&amp;rsquo;s always dangerous to try and measure/quantify performance too much, as it&amp;rsquo;s easy to confuse the metric
with the intended performance. But obviously some of that is necessary just for orientation purposes. If you get lost,
you lose!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mark Rounding</title>
      <link>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/mark-rounding/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 May 2017 09:27:46 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/mark-rounding/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;This is a blog post on sailing. Hence it might contain a number of weird terms and concepts. But sailing
is really very easy and straight forward. It&amp;rsquo;s only when you are racing that it gets a bit more complicated
with rules and tactics!&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.midlandsailingclub.org.uk&#34;&gt;Midland Sailing Club&lt;/a&gt; we race regularly, and sometimes with a
mass start (where all boats start at the same time) rather than a staggered start where the slower boats start
first, and the faster boats later (because they are faster and are expected to catch up). As I haven&amp;rsquo;t been
racing for very long (just over a year now), I&amp;rsquo;m usually somewhere towards the end of the field. But I&amp;rsquo;m slowly
improving and working my way forwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday we had our first race in the Flag Officer Series, which is an average lap race, so all boats start at the
same time, and the Race Officer measures how fast they go round the course. Each class of boat has a handicap, so that
slower boats get a bonus over faster boats (because they are slower). The photo below shows the field just before the
start. I am in the boat with the blue sails (an &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enterprise_(dinghy)&#34;&gt;Enterprise&lt;/a&gt;).
As you can see, the majority of boats are to the right of the start line, whereas I am on the left. The little yellow
buoy with the flag is the end of the start line; the other end is the committee boat, which is obscured by the raft
of boats in front of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ojmason.github.io/img/wedrace_small.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Wednesday Evening race (by @ikonic_exposure)&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually one end of the start line works better than the other, and that seemed to have been the case yesterday, as
most of the boats were at that end. However, one disadvantage is that your wind gets messed up when there are lots of
boats clumped together, and wind is basically your fuel. I started on the left, which was less advantageous, but I had
&amp;lsquo;clean air&amp;rsquo;, as there were few other boats around me. As a result, I had an excellent start, and was going really fast
in front of the fleet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Enterprise is not the fastest of boats, I was not first at the windward mark, but I was in the top group. Now,
normally when I reach a mark, there are no other boats there (because they&amp;rsquo;ll have gone already), but this time there
was quite a group. I came in on port tack, so did not have right of way. And consequently I had to make sure not to
hit any other boats or get in their way, so I had to sail in a circle and join the end of the queue. I lost a lot
of places and was suddenly third from the bottom or so. Not good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why did I do that? I hadn&amp;rsquo;t really been in that situation before.
If I had realised that I was at the mark in the top group, I should
have gone further to the right hand side and come in to the mark
on starboard tack (having right of way).  Then all would have been
well. But because I am so rarely in that situation, I didn&amp;rsquo;t plan
ahead. Bad tactics. Sad!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while I didn&amp;rsquo;t do very well in that race in the end, I am still pleased with the first part, and I think I learned
a lot. The main thing is to plan ahead when approaching a mark, to take into account that there might be a lot of other
boats that I need to take care of, and to have some idea of what tactics to follow. The other main point is not to
worry too much about start line bias. This, however, is the main thing you are told about racing: work out which
end of the start line is favoured (ie closer to the wind), and start from there. But that&amp;rsquo;s what most people do, so
the favoured end is thus the busiest, and
sailing in a big cluster of boats is slow. I started slightly behind at the unfavoured end, but was able to sail much
faster and unimpeded in clean air, so the fact that I started a few boat lengths behind the field did not matter at
all. I suspect for most people it will be the same. It&amp;rsquo;s also less stressful, as you don&amp;rsquo;t have to worry about
colliding with other boats on the start line! This is recommended by the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.impropercourse.com/2013/05/sailing-in-middle-of-fleet-clean-air.html&#34;&gt;Improper Course Blog&lt;/a&gt; where I got
the idea from. Or rather, the reassurance not to have to do what everybody else does (and tells you to do!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will have a chance to try that out over the next two weekends, where I will be at two Enterprise Open meetings
(where we all race in the same class of boat) at Barnt Green and Tamworth. Mass start, though probably fewer boats.
And then I will have a proper think about tactics in advance!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS: We came &lt;a href=&#34;https://midlandsailing.club/sailwave/2016-17/flagofficerseriesalh.html#r1&#34;&gt;14th out of 21 boats&lt;/a&gt;, which is quite a good result. Pretty much everybody who ended up ahead of me is
a better sailor, and I even beat some of the more experienced racers in their fast boats. So I&amp;rsquo;m pleased, especially
given the places I lost at the first mark!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;Photo &amp;copy; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.daniel-sturley.com/index.html&#34;&gt;Daniel Sturley&lt;/a&gt;, used with permission&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Streak of Damocles</title>
      <link>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/the-streak-of-damocles/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 May 2017 15:28:48 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/the-streak-of-damocles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Streaks are a well-know means of establishing habits. You do something every day, and count how many consecutive
days you have had in a run. Each day adds one to the streak. And puts on the pressure not to break it. You do not
want to get back to &amp;ldquo;0 days since the last time I forgot to do X&amp;rdquo;. Pressure to do it equals motivation. A positive
feedback loop: the longer the streak, the more pressure. Until you snap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have built up almost 600 days of uninterrupted language learning on Duolingo. That is partly because I managed
to fit it into my daily routine, so I have no difficulty doing two lessons (my daily target) every day. It is
difficult sometimes when travelling, as your daily routine is different then, and I nearly lost the streak because
of a timezone issue. In a way the streak is not why I&amp;rsquo;m learning, though. I have an intrinsic motivation (wanting
to improve my language skills), and the streak maintenance is more for the benefit of keeping track how long I&amp;rsquo;ve
been doing this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My daughters also use Duolingo (not so much anymore, though), and one of them had a longish streak, and then lost it,
as she was too busy one day doing the multitude of other things she does. That pretty much killed her motivation for
quite some time. Elsewhere on the internet there are similar stories of people who lost streaks due to circumstances
outside their control, with a negative effect on their motivation. Even if you still want to learn the language (or
do whatever activity you want to establish as a habit), it&amp;rsquo;s a punch that you first need to recover from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like so many ideas, streaks as a motivational tool sound good, but they have their own problems. I don&amp;rsquo;t know what
would happen if I lost my streak. While I hope it would not bother me, it still might affect my willingness to
continue. I just don&amp;rsquo;t know. So here the pressure that has built up over time is clearly negative through the
uncertainty it introduces. On previous occasions, streaks have helped me to maintain a habit for a limited period
of time, but never as long as with my language skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was still working as an academic, I set myself a target of writing at least 1000 words every day. It went up
to the point that I went to bed, realised I hadn&amp;rsquo;t done any writing, jumped out again and sat in front of the computer
until I had done it. While I managed to do that for quite a while, at some point it just petered out. If you have
to force yourself to do something, then streaks will not help you. My Duolingo habit supports this: I am genuinely
interested and motivated to learn, and two lessons a day is an easily manageable task. The writing target I had set
myself was probably too ambitious to maintain in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you use streaks merely to keep track for how long you have done something, then they are probaby alright. But if
they become your main motivational driver, then I would think they have missed their purpose. And losing your streak
might well lead you to abandoning the task you wanted to habitualise.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Home</title>
      <link>https://ojmason.github.io/defaultsite/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ojmason.github.io/defaultsite/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello, I&amp;rsquo;m Oliver. I am a computational linguist, interested in applications
of NLP and AI in understanding texts and conversing with human beings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a passionate dinghy sailor, sailing an &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enterprise_(dinghy)&#34;&gt;Enterprise&lt;/a&gt;
or a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laser_(dinghy)&#34;&gt;Laser&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Midland_Sailing_Club&#34;&gt;Midland
Sailing Club&lt;/a&gt; in the UK. I am also a qualified Dinghy Instructor, and run the
RYA training centre at the club.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Toki Pona</title>
      <link>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/toki-pona/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2017 11:27:24 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/toki-pona/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since working in computational linguistics I have been interested in constructed languages (&amp;lsquo;conlangs&amp;rsquo;).
When trying to process any natural language with computer programs, you constantly run into inconvenient
exceptions, in morphology, syntax, etc. A conlang such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Esperanto&#34;&gt;Esperanto&lt;/a&gt;
promises a great simplification: as it is completely regular, NLP software is likely to be much simpler and
less complex. However, given that Esperanto is a full-scale language, it&amp;rsquo;s still not trivial to work with. It&amp;rsquo;s
got a large vocabulary, and the syntax is not that easy to parse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a post on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://esperanto.stackexchange.com/&#34;&gt;Esperanto Language Stack Exchange&lt;/a&gt; I then heard of another
conlang, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toki_Pona&#34;&gt;Toki Pona&lt;/a&gt;. This is billed as a &lt;em&gt;minimalist&lt;/em&gt; language: it only
has about 120 words, and a very fixed and simplistic sentence structure. Unlike Esperanto, it is not really a
proper language for everyday use, but more of a philosophical experiment. How does your language influence the
way you think about the world? This is kind of related to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linguistic_relativity&#34;&gt;Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis&lt;/a&gt;.
When you have to limit yourself to describing/paraphrasing everything with a limited vocabulary, you need to
reflect more about what it is you&amp;rsquo;re talking about. For example, a friend is a &lt;em&gt;jan pona&lt;/em&gt; (&amp;lsquo;good person&amp;rsquo;), and a
bad person is a &lt;em&gt;jan ike&lt;/em&gt;. So how do you say &amp;lsquo;bad friend&amp;rsquo;? You are not able to say someone is both good and bad
at the same time. So a friend cannot be a bad person, or vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toki Pona arguably is a toy language only. There is just one word for &lt;em&gt;fruit&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;vegetable&lt;/em&gt;, etc.: &lt;em&gt;kili&lt;/em&gt;. If you want
to say &lt;em&gt;banana&lt;/em&gt;, you say &lt;em&gt;kili jelo&lt;/em&gt; (&amp;ldquo;yellow fruit&amp;rdquo;). If you want to talk about lemons as well, you&amp;rsquo;re out of luck.
It&amp;rsquo;s very context dependent, and definitely not useful for a scientific treatise, or even recipes. But it&amp;rsquo;s fine
for basic stories, myths and legends, and so on. And, most importantly, it&amp;rsquo;s easy to learn. No morphology. Very
limited syntax. Small vocabulary. The main difficulty is to express yourself given those limited means. But
we grow only when challenged!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m interested in doing NLP with Toki Pona, as it is so limited. It should be possible to quickly get to the semantic
or pragmatic levels, as morphology and syntax will be dealt with easily. Analysing and generating sentences should
be extremely easy. More on that as it materialises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in languages, and what to explore the way you express meaning, give Toki Pona a try. There
are various on-line resources available, plus a text book &lt;a href=&#34;http://amzn.to/2oN4Zo7&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toki Pona &amp;ndash; The Language of Good&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll post more on this at a later time&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>History Repeats Itself</title>
      <link>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/history-repeats-itself/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2017 11:11:30 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/history-repeats-itself/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At the AAAI-84 conference, more than 30 years ago, was a panel discussion on &lt;em&gt;The Dark Ages of AI&lt;/em&gt;. Drew McDermott
said in the article in AI Magazine (vol 6 no 3 1985):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In spite of all the commercial hustle and bustle around AI these days there&amp;rsquo;s a mood [&amp;hellip;] of deep unease among
AI reserachers [&amp;hellip;]. This unease is due to the worry that that perhaps expectations about AI are too high,
and that this will eventually end in disaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a real feeling of deja-vu. We have been there before, in the late 1960s, when the failed promises of
instant high-quality machine translation caused what was dubbed the &lt;em&gt;AI Winter&lt;/em&gt;, with all research funding
being stopped. AI recovered, and twenty years later the same happened. And now again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The situation has somewhat changed, as we have an abundance of data and processing power, but still no intelligence.
The algorithms are still the same old ones we had before, only on a larger scale.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artificial_neural_network&#34;&gt;Artificial neural networks&lt;/a&gt; are faster,
and with &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deep_learning&#34;&gt;Deep Learning&lt;/a&gt; they have become easier to use. We are replacing human engineering work (feature selection etc)
by clever algorithms and are letting the machine find things out by itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is that it works fine in some situations, and then it suddenly becomes the magic bullet. Everybody now has
to do Deep Learning, as it has become the new marketing buzzword. AI is everywhere, but also nowhere, really. We do
not know anything more about the world than we did before, but we can get fast computers to recognise patterns in
data. &lt;a href=&#34;https://ojmason.github.io/blog/arguable-intelligence/&#34;&gt;No intelligence there&lt;/a&gt;. And if you are trying to calm down expectations you are not
&amp;lsquo;disruptive&amp;rsquo; enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is only a question of time until it all comes crashing down, and AI will be be blamed for empty promises. We&amp;rsquo;ve
been there before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all fits into the overall pattern of human behaviour. In Europe we are forgetting the lessons from the early
20th century, and nationalism is on the rise; it might seem a bit over the top to compare the current situation to
1930s Germany, but the point is that at the time people didn&amp;rsquo;t know what was happening. We now have the benefit of
knowing where it can lead to, and it would be foolish to ignore the warning signs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In AI as in society: history always repeats itself, and if you forget the past, you are condemmed to repeat it.
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Santayana&#34;&gt;George Santayana&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: thanks to @DiegoKuonen for tweeting the reference to the AAAI-84 paper.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arguable Intelligence</title>
      <link>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/arguable-intelligence/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2017 16:45:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/arguable-intelligence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I work in the field of AI. I studied it at university, I read books about AI in my spare time,
implement toy systems that operate in the field, and I try to keep uptodate with current developments.
And it infuriates me&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artificial Intelligence has moved from an academic/applied subject to a marketing buzzword. Every
washing machine is now &amp;ldquo;powered by AI&amp;rdquo;. So AI means everything and nothing these days. Let&amp;rsquo;s look at
the traditional definitions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Hard AI&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;the cognitive processes of human beings are implemented in software. By doing so, a computer
basically functions like a human being, the brain being equivalent to a micro processor.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Soft AI&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;the cognitive system of a human being is imitated by computer software. There is no claim that
this models human cognition, but the outcomes are the same.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This dichotomy was current when I learned about AI. But now there is a new element which arose in the
past couple of decades with the availability of large amounts of data in all sorts of domains: machine
learning (ML). In ML you basically train a mathematical model with data, which allows you to classify
other data items (which your system has not seen before). Or maybe map between one item (eg an English phrase)
and another (eg an equivalent German phrase). The difference here is that there is &lt;em&gt;no human cognition involved&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI is a direct reference to cognition, hence the &amp;lsquo;I&amp;rsquo; of it, but ML is not. It&amp;rsquo;s an automaton, which has no
understanding of what it is doing. In early AI systems, domain knowledge was usually modelled in a
representation system, a logical language, a semantic network, whatever.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knowledge_representation_and_reasoning&#34;&gt;Knowledge representation&lt;/a&gt; was/is an
important aspect of AI, as you cannot have AI without knowledge. In an ML system, knowledge is encoded in
model parameters, numerical values that have no meaning outside the model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One point that motivates me to work in AI is that we learn about how humans process the world. We find out what
is important, how me make decision, how we evaluate what is better or worse. In ML we just feed a black box with
examples that we have marked up as good or bad, and we get a black box that can distinguish between these categories
with a more or less acceptable accuracy. What have we learned about the process of making that distinction?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To re-iterate, machine learning is not artificial intelligence. It is statistical engineering. I&amp;rsquo;m not denying
that it is useful, but calling it AI is plain wrong, and will undoubtedly lead to a new
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AI_winter&#34;&gt;AI winter&lt;/a&gt; once the bubble bursts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title> Software is Sh*t</title>
      <link>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/software-is-sht/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2017 15:00:26 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/software-is-sht/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;software-is-sh-t&#34;&gt;Software is sh*t&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to get back into blogging, the easy way. A minimal, static website,
easy to publish stuff, no big overheads, control over what I write. I looked at
hosting pages on github, which seemed like a good enough option. Github pages suggest
something called Jekyll as a generator for the site &amp;ndash; much better than manually coding
everything up in HTML and linking stuff by hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a nightmare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why, in 2017, is it harder to install some dinky piece of software than it was 20 years
ago? Why do I need to download half the packages on the internet to resolve dependencies?
And what do I do (as it invariably happens) when somthing falls over with a cryptic error
message? It&amp;rsquo;s enough to turn you into a grumpy old man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then one of my twitter friends recommended Hugo. Installation was fine, only then github
was confused. It is already well known that &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; is not exactly the pinnacle of usability,
and it doesn&amp;rsquo;t help that it seems to become the default tool for any command-line job. I can
see that a website can be modelled with a repository, and it&amp;rsquo;s probably a good idea, but
git seems such an overkill for 90% of what you would want to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several attempts and hours later I have a basic site running. But, no white space between the
date and title of the blog post. And no idea how to fix that. Gah. Maybe it would have been
better to just hand-code everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is understandable that website generation is complex. This can easily be seen by the number of
generators available for doing so. Everybody who tries to use one seems to find it complicated and
illogical, and then writes their own. Which slowly grows into a behemoth that is complicated and
illogical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might sound arrogant and elitist, but I think software engineering is harder than many people
think. It&amp;rsquo;s always easier to start a new project than to maintain and curate an existing one. As
a logical consequence we have a proliferation of software projects, mostly doing the same things
in different ways. And few of them are of a high enough standard to be properly usable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really wanted to end this post on a constructive note, but I don&amp;rsquo;t think I&amp;rsquo;m able to.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title> First Post</title>
      <link>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2017 14:40:17 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/first-post/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;first-post&#34;&gt;First Post&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m trying blogging again &amp;ndash; twitter is a bit too sparse for longer rants. And this seems
to be a time for rants. Lots happening in politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, here we go again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update:&lt;/em&gt; I&amp;rsquo;m also going through my previous WordPress log to gather some articles that
might still be interesting, so there will be older articles going back almost a decade
appearing here.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>