<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Press on Arguable Intelligence</title>
    <link>https://ojmason.github.io/categories/press/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Press on Arguable Intelligence</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <copyright>(C) Oliver Mason</copyright>
    <atom:link href="https://ojmason.github.io/categories/press/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Numerical Illiteracy</title>
      <link>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/numerical-illiteracy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/numerical-illiteracy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note:&lt;/em&gt; This is an older article from the blog I ran while being an academic. Most of the posts
on there are about teaching and learning, but this one is of more general relevance, see also
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ojmason.github.io/longest-chip-in-the-world/&#34;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;hr&gt;
I had a look at our free local newspaper, the &lt;em&gt;Birmingham Mail Extra&lt;/em&gt;.
In this issue is an article titled &amp;ldquo;Suburb is now crime hotspot&amp;rdquo;.
This article has several problems, which are indicative of the
problems of representing what happens &amp;lsquo;out there&amp;rsquo; in the form of a
newspaper article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quinton had very little burglaries, &amp;ldquo;averaging just one or two
burglaries a month&amp;rdquo; over the last nine years. But now, crime has
&amp;ldquo;shot up by 29%&amp;rdquo;, more than the rest of Birmingham where crime only
rose by 21%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find this rather misleading, and I worked through an example with
the kids at the dinner table, which illustrates the problem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suburb A had 10 burglaries in 2009, and 12 in 2010. That is an increase of 20%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suburb B had 4 burglaries in 2009, and 5 in 2010. Increase of 25%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suburb C had 1 burglary in 2009, and 2 in 2010. A whopping 100% increase.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;First lesson:&lt;/em&gt; percentage increase is meaningless unless everybody
started in the same place. Why do developing economies have higher
growth rates than Europe and the US? Because the percentage looks
bigger. If you double your output from 100 cars to 200 cars you
increase by 100%, but to maintain that rate you will have to produce
an additional 200 cars the year after, and then 400, 800 etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Second lesson:&lt;/em&gt; without a fixed reference point (such as burglaries
per 1000 inhabitants) you have no idea whether the risk of your
house being burgled is high or low. Everything is relative, but you
still need a fixed point to evaluate things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Third lesson:&lt;/em&gt; this is not mentioned, but is that difference between
29% and 21% statistically significant? With &amp;ldquo;one or two burglaries
a month&amp;rdquo;, the variation seems rather high, given those small numbers.
So if there was one extra or one fewer burglaries, how would the
29% change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Final lesson:&lt;/em&gt; be careful with calling places &amp;ldquo;crime hotspot&amp;rdquo; when
your statistics are that shaky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I don&amp;rsquo;t expect a staff reporter at the &lt;em&gt;Birmingham Mail&lt;/em&gt; to apply
the same rigour as a scientist (or any other, non-science researcher),
but the way the article is presented is simply misleading. To me
this sounds like a scare story being created out of some random
statistics. I don&amp;rsquo;t know whether that is the case, and maybe Quinton
is really a crime-ridden area, but I cannot tell from the few facts
given to me in the article. The reason for this development given
in the paper is that there are now 5 fewer policemen covering
Quinton. Is there really such a cast-iron correlation between
policemen and crime rate? How about the influence of the recession
on crime? And how many policemen were there before the cut? 50? 500?
5000?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now have more questions and know less than I did before reading
that article!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>