<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Erlang on Arguable Intelligence</title>
    <link>https://ojmason.github.io/categories/erlang/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Erlang on Arguable Intelligence</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <atom:link href="https://ojmason.github.io/categories/erlang/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Solving Combinatory Problems with Erlang</title>
      <link>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/solving-combinatory-problems-with-erlang/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/solving-combinatory-problems-with-erlang/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My daughter had some maths homework the other day:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have 4 bags, each full of the numbers 1, 3, 5, and 7 respectively.
Take 10 of the numbers that when added up make 37. What numbers are they?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far so good: that sounds easy enough. But a bit of trial and
error quickly leads nowhere. Something can’t be right. So, let’s
get the computer to work it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I haven’t done much Erlang recently I thought I’d give it a go.
And, during a casual glance at Armstrong’s &lt;em&gt;Programming in Erlang&lt;/em&gt; I
thought I’d finally understood list comprehensions, so I wrote the
following program:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
-module(comb).
-export([result/0]).
result() -&gt;
[{A+B+C+D+E+F+G+H+I+J,A,B,C,D,E,F,G,H,I,J}||
A &lt;- [1,3,5,7],
B &lt;- [1,3,5,7],
C &lt;- [1,3,5,7],
D &lt;- [1,3,5,7],
E &lt;- [1,3,5,7],
F &lt;- [1,3,5,7],
G &lt;- [1,3,5,7],
H &lt;- [1,3,5,7],
I &lt;- [1,3,5,7],
J &lt;- [1,3,5,7],
A+B+C+D+E+F+G+H+I+J =:= 37].
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I declare a module with one function, &lt;code&gt;result/0&lt;/code&gt;. This finds me ten
variables that can take any of the four specified values and add
up to 37. Simples!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The list comprehension has ten generators, and one filter; it will
return a tuple with the sum and the individual variables’ values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
Erlang R16B01 (erts-5.10.2) [64-bit] [smp:4:4] [async-threads:10] [hipe] [kernel-poll:false]
Eshell V5.10.2 (abort with ^G)
1&gt; comb:result().
[]
2&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WTF???! An empty list?! So I try changing the 37 to another value, like 36.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
3&gt; comb:result().
[{36,1,1,1,1,1,3,7,7,7,7},
{36,1,1,1,1,1,5,5,7,7,7},
{36,1,1,1,1,1,5,7,5,7,7},
{36,1,1,1,1,1,5,7,7,5,7},
{36,1,1,1,1,1,5,7,7,7,5},
[etc, etc].
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it does work! Only, there doesn’t seem to be an answer to the
question. And with a bit of logical reasoning it is obvious: when
adding two odd numbers, you get an even number. So adding ten odd
numbers also yields an even number, but 37 is odd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I learnt from this exercise: thinking about the problem
beforehand can save you time, as there was no need to write a program
at all. But then, I did get to use list comprehensions, and have
learnt how powerful they are. And it neatly shows Erlang’s Prolog
roots as well.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Replacing a stack with concurrency</title>
      <link>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/replacing-a-stack-with-concurrency/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/replacing-a-stack-with-concurrency/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For some language processing task I needed a reasonably powerful
parser (a program to identify the syntactic structure of a sentence).
So I dug out my copy of Winograd (1983) (&lt;em&gt;Language as a Cognitive
Process&lt;/em&gt;) and set about implementing an &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Augmented_transition_network&#34;&gt;Augmented Transition Network&lt;/a&gt;
parser in Erlang.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the first thing you learn about natural language is that it
is full of ambiguities, and so there will always be several
alternatives available, several possible paths through the network
which defines the grammar. The traditional solution is to dump all
the alternatives on a stack, and look at them when the current path
has been finished with. You can either go depth-first, where you
complete the current path before you get the next one off the stack,
or breadth-first, where you advance all paths by one step at a time,
kind of pseudo-parallel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having to deal with a stack is tedious, as you need to keep track
of the current configuration: which network are you at, what node,
what position in the sentence, etc. But then, it occurred to me,
there’s an easier way to do it (at least it’s easier in Erlang!):
every time you come to a point where you have multiple alternatives,
you spawn a new process and pursue all of them in parallel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only overhead you need is a loop which keeps track of all the
processes currently running. This loop receives the results of
successful paths, and gets notified of unsuccessful ones (where the
process terminates without having found a valid structure). No need
for a stack, and hopefully very efficient processing on multi-core
machines as a free side-effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m still amazed how easy it was to implement. I wouldn’t have
fancied doing that in Java or even C. For my test sentences I had
about 8 to 10 processes running in parallel most of the time, but
it depends on the size of the grammar and the length of the sentence
really. What I liked about this was that it seemed the natural way
to do in Erlang, where working with processes is just so easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And also, another nail in the coffin for the claim that you can’t
use Erlang for handling texts easily!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>