<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Politics on Arguable Intelligence</title>
    <link>https://ojmason.github.io/categories/politics/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Politics on Arguable Intelligence</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <copyright>(C) Oliver Mason</copyright>
    <atom:link href="https://ojmason.github.io/categories/politics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Party Politics and the Emperor&#39;s New Clothes</title>
      <link>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/party-politics-and-the-emperors-new-clothes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/party-politics-and-the-emperors-new-clothes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On Twitter I came across a link to the (German) &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cdu.de/sites/default/files/media/dokumente/regierungsprogramm-in-leichter-sprache-btw13.pdf&#34;&gt;CDU Wahlprogramm in “Leichter Sprache”&lt;/a&gt;.
This is the conservative party’s election manifesto in a German
version of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basic_English&#34;&gt;Basic English&lt;/a&gt;,
to make it more easily comprehensible to
people who have difficulty understanding standard German.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first I thought it was a parody, as it sounded truly ridiculous
and patronising. As if you had to explain to your 4-year-old what
the world was like. Then I found out about the “&lt;a href=&#34;http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leichte_Sprache&#34;&gt;Leichte Sprache&lt;/a&gt;”
(literally: “&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plain_language&#34;&gt;easy/plain language&lt;/a&gt;“), which I had not heard of before.
And in principle it is a noble thing to do, to make your manifesto
more accessible. I’m sure &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mtholyoke.edu/acad/intrel/orwell46.htm&#34;&gt;George Orwell&lt;/a&gt; would approve!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the real reason why it does seem strange is rooted in the nature
of political language: normally, language is used to obfuscate and
manipulate, especially in complex areas such as politics. Fancy
words are used to disguise true intentions and get people to vote
for you. But take away the fancy words and complex phrases, and
suddenly all is out there in the open, plain to see for everybody.
And it turns out to be pretty meaningless. “Everybody should have
a good job. And earn enough money. That needs to be written down.”
But no mention about minimum wage or anything concrete to turn those
vacuous phrases into reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some other people on twitter reacted in the same way as I did; often
I guess out of the same ignorance of the “easy language” concept.
That’s a shame, but partly rooted in the patronising way the sentences
come across. But it also shows that the (undesired) outcome of this
publication is that people tend to not take the content seriously.
Because there is not much of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Critical_discourse_analysis&#34;&gt;Critical Discourse Analysis&lt;/a&gt;
would lose a big part of its subject
area if politics would switch wholesale to “easy language”. No more
subconscious manipulation between the lines, no more obfuscation
about who does what to whom. So after some reflection I applaud the
CDU for making their manifesto available in this way, as it unmasks
them as the patronising right-wingers they are, with their overly
simplistic world view about pretty much any subject area in current
politics. No more hiding behind fancy words that foreigners are not
welcome. No more vague claims about surveillance cameras stopping
crime. It’s all there, in plain language. And other parties seem
to have done the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the only thing that needs to go is the disclaimer at the
beginning: that this plain version is not the real manifesto, and
only the real one does count. I would prefer it to be the other way
round.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>