<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Toki Pona on Arguable Intelligence</title>
    <link>https://ojmason.github.io/categories/toki-pona/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Toki Pona on Arguable Intelligence</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <copyright>(C) Oliver Mason</copyright>
    <atom:link href="https://ojmason.github.io/categories/toki-pona/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Toki Pona</title>
      <link>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/toki-pona/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2017 11:27:24 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/toki-pona/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since working in computational linguistics I have been interested in constructed languages (&amp;lsquo;conlangs&amp;rsquo;).
When trying to process any natural language with compute programs, you constantly run into inconvenient
exceptions, in morphology, syntax, etc. A conlang such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Esperanto&#34;&gt;Esperanto&lt;/a&gt;
promises a great simplification: as it is completely regular, NLP software is likely to be much simpler and
less complex. However, given that Esperanto is a full-scale language, it&amp;rsquo;s still not trivial to work with. It&amp;rsquo;s
got a large vocabulary, and the syntax is not that easy to parse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a post on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://esperanto.stackexchange.com/&#34;&gt;Esperanto Language Stack Exchange&lt;/a&gt; I then heard of another
conlang, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toki_Pona&#34;&gt;Toki Pona&lt;/a&gt;. This is billed as a &lt;em&gt;minimalist&lt;/em&gt; language: it only
has about 120 words, and a very fixed and simplistic sentence structure. Unlike Esperanto, it is not really a
proper language for everyday use, but more of a philosophical experiment. How does your language influence the
way you think about the world? This is kind of related to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linguistic_relativity&#34;&gt;Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis&lt;/a&gt;.
When you have to limit yourself to describing/paraphrasing everything with a limited vocabulary, you need to
reflect more about what it is you&amp;rsquo;re talking about. For example, a friend is a &lt;em&gt;jan pona&lt;/em&gt; (&amp;lsquo;good person&amp;rsquo;), and a
bad person is a &lt;em&gt;jan ike&lt;/em&gt;. So how do you say &amp;lsquo;bad friend&amp;rsquo;? You are not able to say someone is both good and bad
at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toki Pona arguably is a toy language only. There is just one word for &lt;em&gt;fruit&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;vegetable&lt;/em&gt;, etc.: &lt;em&gt;kili&lt;/em&gt;. If you want
to say &lt;em&gt;banana&lt;/em&gt;, you say &lt;em&gt;kili jelo&lt;/em&gt; (&amp;ldquo;yellow fruit&amp;rdquo;). If you want to talk about lemons as well, you&amp;rsquo;re out of luck.
It&amp;rsquo;s very context dependent, and definitely not useful for scientific treatise, or even recipes. But it&amp;rsquo;s fine
for basic stories, myths and legends, and so on. And, most importantly, it&amp;rsquo;s easy to learn. No morphology. Very
limited syntax. Small vocabulary. The main difficulty is to express yourself given those limited means. But
we grow only when challenged!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m interested in doing NLP with Toki Pona, as it is so limited. It should be possible to quickly get to the semantic
or pragmatic levels, as morphology and syntax will be dealt with easily. Analysing and generating sentences should
be extremely easy. More on that as it materialises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in languages, and what to explore the way you express meaning, give Toki Pona a try. There
are various on-line resources available, plus a text book &lt;a href=&#34;http://amzn.to/2oN4Zo7&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toki Pona &amp;ndash; The Language of Good&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll post more on this at a later time&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>