<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sailing on Arguable Intelligence</title>
    <link>https://ojmason.github.io/categories/sailing/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Sailing on Arguable Intelligence</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <copyright>(C) Oliver Mason</copyright>
    <atom:link href="https://ojmason.github.io/categories/sailing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Mark Rounding</title>
      <link>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/mark-rounding/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 May 2017 09:27:46 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ojmason.github.io/blog/mark-rounding/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;This is a blog post on sailing. Hence it might contain a number of weird terms and concepts. But sailing
is really very easy and straight forward. It&amp;rsquo;s only when you are racing that it gets a bit more complicated
with rules and tactics!&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.midlandsailingclub.org.uk&#34;&gt;Midland Sailing Club&lt;/a&gt; we race regularly, and sometimes with a
mass start (where all boats start at the same time) rather than a staggered start where the slower boats start
first, and the faster boats later (because they are faster and are expected to catch up). As I haven&amp;rsquo;t been
racing for very long (just over a year now), I&amp;rsquo;m usually somewhere towards the end of the field. But I&amp;rsquo;m slowly
improving and working my way forwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday we had our first race in the Flag Officer Series, which is an average lap race, so all boats start at the
same time, and the Race Officer measures how fast they go round the course. Each class of boat has a handicap, so that
slower boats get a bonus over faster boats (because they are slower). The photo below shows the field just before the
start. I am in the boat with the blue sails (an &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enterprise_(dinghy)&#34;&gt;Enterprise&lt;/a&gt;).
As you can see, the majority of boats are to the right of the start line, whereas I am on the left. The little yellow
buoy with the flag is the end of the start line; the other end is the committee boat, which is obscured by the raft
of boats in front of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ojmason.github.io/img/wedrace_small.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Wednesday Evening race (by @ikonic_exposure)&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually one end of the start line works better than the other, and that seemed to have been the case yesterday, as
most of the boats were at that end. However, one disadvantage is that your wind gets messed up when there are lots of
boats clumoed together, and wind is basically your fuel. I started on the left, which was less advantageous, but I had
&amp;lsquo;clean air&amp;rsquo;, as there were few other boats around me. As a result, I had an excellent start, and was going really fast
in front of the fleet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Enterprise is not the fastest of boats, I was not first at the windward mark, but I was in the top group. Now,
normally when I reach a mark, there are no other boats there (because they&amp;rsquo;ll have gone already), but this time there
was quite a group. I came in on port tack, so did not have right of way. And consequently I had to make sure not to
hit any other boats or get in their way, so I had to sail in a circle and join the end of the queue. I lost a lot
of places and was suddenly third from the bottom or so. Not good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why did I do that? I wasn&amp;rsquo;t really in that situation before. If I had realised that I was at the mark in the top group,
I should have gone further to the right hand side and come in to the mark on starboard tack (having right of way).
Then all would have been well. But because I am so rarely in that situation, I didn&amp;rsquo;t plan ahead. Bad tactics. Sad!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while I didn&amp;rsquo;t do very well in that race in the end, I am still pleased with the first part, and I think I learned
a lot. The main thing is to plan ahead when approaching a mark, to take into account that there might be a lot of other
boats that I need to take care of, and to have some idea of what tactics to follow. The other main point is not to
worry too much about start line bias. This, however, is the main thing you are told about racing: work out which
end of the start line is favoured (ie closer to the wind), and start from there. But that&amp;rsquo;s what most people do, and
sailing in a big cluster of boats is slow. I started slightly behind at the unfavoured end, but was able to sail much
faster and unimpeded in clean air, so the fact that I started a few boat lengths behind the field did not matter at
all. I suspect for most people it will be the same. It&amp;rsquo;s also less stressful, as you don&amp;rsquo;t have to worry about
colliding with other boats on the start line!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will have a chance to try that out over the next two weekends, where I will be at two Enterprise Open meetings
(where we all race in the same class of boat) at Barnt Green and Tamworth. Mass start, though probably fewer boats.
And then I will have a proper think about tactics in advance!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>